Guide to the Larry L. King Papers
The Wittliff Collections
Larry L. King Papers
1929-1993
The Wittliff Collections https://www.thewittliffcollections.txstate.edu
King, Larry L.
SWWC.006
39 boxes
19 Linear Feet
The Larry L. King papers document his writing career and span the years from 1929 to 1993 with most of the material dating from the late 1950s.
Scope and Contents
The Larry L. King papers span the years from 1929 to 1993 with most of the material dating from the late 1950s. They are arranged according to the following eleven series: 1. Books; 2. Plays; 3. Articles; 4. Short stories 5. Television; 6. Songs; 7. Speeches; 8. Material about King; 9. Other Writers; 10. Personal Papers; 11. Correspondence.
Within the archive are manuscripts, galley proofs, magazines, tear sheets, playbooks, flyers, posters, tapes, videos, clippings, correspondence, calendars, cancelled checks, tax receipts, vital records, photographs, T-shirts, a jacket and a typewriter. These materials document King's life and career and provide a thorough overview of his writing process. They include correspondence with or about other Texas writers, such as Larry McMurtry, Bud Shrake, Billy Lee Brammer, Dan Jenkins, Peter Gent, Jay Milner and Gary Cartwright along with letters to friends and family such as cousin Lanvil Gilbert and colorful Texas lawyer, Warren Burnett. The materials are most frequently arranged in chronological order.
Contact the The Wittliff Collections for information about additional materials from this writer that have not yet been fully processed.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of Larry L. King, Russell Harding and Lanvil Gilbert since 1987.
Biographical Notes
Lawrence Leo King, the youngest child of Clyde Clayton and Cora Lee Clark King, was born January 1, 1929 in Putnam, Texas. He fixed on a career as a writer early in his childhood, inspired by the Mark Twain his mother read to him. As early as grade school, King pursued publication of his works. He wrote regularly for the student newspaper at high school where he found a mentor in Aubra Nooncaster, football coach, English teacher and poet. From high school, King joined the army where he was a reporter for his base paper. He wrote professionally as a sports and crime reporter for the Hobbs (N. M.) Daily Flare, the Midland Reporter-Telegram and the Odessa American after a brief stint at Texas Technological College (now Texas Tech University) as a journalism major. In 1954, King moved to Washington, D.C. as the Administrative Assistant to Representative J. T. Rutherford. After Rutherford was defeated in 1962, King joined the staff of another Texas congressman, future House Speaker Jim Wright. In 1964, King quit Capitol Hill to become a free-lance writer.
The novel, The One-Eyed Man, was published in 1966, but King's chief livelihood as a writer during this time came from his magazine articles. From 1964, King wrote for The Texas Observer, an iconoclastic liberal magazine "then the only voice of dissent (constant) or reason (occasionally) to be found in my native state" (King, Blockhead 20). At the same time, Mississippian Willie Morris, a University of Texas graduate and former editor of the Observer, encouraged King's writing ambitions. Morris gave King his first national exposure in Harper's, where Morris was an editor. In 1967, Morris was named editor-in-chief of Harper's and under his leadership, the magazine became famed for its' exciting and innovative writing. Morris published the brightest literary lights of the day as represented by an impressive list King catalogues in The Old Man and Lesser Mortals: "James Dickey, Jules Feiffer, Robert Penn Warren, Justin Kaplan, Sara Davidson, Jack Richardson, Elizabeth Hardwick, Norman Podhoretz, Arthur Miller, Tony Lucas, George Plimpton, Bud Shrake, Michael Arlen, Joe McGinnis, Alfred Kazin, John Updike, Ralph Ellison, Jeremy Larner, Ward Just, Truman Capote, Herbert Gold, Tom Wicker, Gay Talese, Larry McMurtry, Joan Didion, Philip Roth, John Fowles, Irving Howe.. ." (286). Not to be left out are William Styron, Norman Mailer, Bill Moyers and David Halberstam. King's best magazine work, as witnessed by the dominance of Harper's pieces in King's published collections, was done under Morris's editing. Examples of their collaboration are "Requiem for a West Texas Town", "My Hero LBJ", "The Old Man", and "The Whole World's Turned On."
King went on to write for numerous, well-known publications including Life, Holiday, Cosmopolitan, The Progressive, Playboy and Sports Illustrated. His topics were, in the main, Texas ("Requiem for a West Texas Town," "The Old Man," "The Lost Frontier," "Playing Cowboy") and politics ("My Hero LBJ," "God, Man and William F. Buckley," "The Trial of John Connally"), but he also treated other subjects such as sports, travel, and music.
In 1978, King penned the book for the hit Broadway musical The Best Little Whorehouse in Texas, based on an article he wrote for Playboy. The success of Whorehouse allowed King to get off what he had come to feel was the magazine treadmill and develop his talent in a different form. He has subsequently seen his plays The Night Hank Williams Died, The Kingfish and Golden Shadows Old West Museum produced.
During his career, King's work has received much praise. He earned a National Book Award Nomination in 1972 for Confessions of a White Racist. He received a Stanley Walker Journalism Award from the Texas Institute of Letters in 1973 for the article "The Lost Frontier." A television documentary, CBS Reports: The Best Little Statehouse in Texas, earned him an Emmy. He received the Mary Goldwater Award from the Theatre Lobby Trust in 1988 for The Night Hank Williams Died. This same work brought him the Helen Hayes award for best new play in 1989.
Though a college dropout, King's journalistic talent brought him to Harvard University in the 1969-1970 academic year as a Nieman Fellow. (He chronicled this experience in the October 1970 issue of Harper's, "Blowing My Mind at Harvard".) From Fall 1973 through Fall 1974, King taught as a Ferris Professor of Journalism and Political Science at Princeton University. He was a Duke Fellow of Communications from 1975 to 1976.
King has lived the majority of his life away from his home state but he continually returns there in his writing. In his own words, "That time and place of my youth -- which, I had been thoroughly convinced contained no story material, has merely provided me with the stuff of a career." (King, National Geographic Speech 1988) By chronicling the Texas that formed him, a Texas that is passing if not past, King, who believes "understanding of the past is vital to the lessons of the present" (King, The Old Man 46) has come to see himself as a leaver of "literary signposts. Those signposts say, simply... this is how it was, in my time and my place, when I passed this way.... Pass it on!" (C.A.S.T. Speech 1993, SWWC).
King married Wilma Jeanne Casey (d. 1991) in 1950. They had three children, Alexandria, Kerri Lee King Grandey, and Bradley Clayton. King, divorced in 1964, married on February 20, 1965 Rosemarie Coumaris Kline, who died of cancer June 8, 1972. Since May 6, 1978, King then married Barbara S. Blaine, who was also his lawyer and agent. They had two children, Lindsay Allison and Blaine Carlton.
King died of emphysema on December 20, 2012.
Index Terms
Subjects
Authors, American -- Texas -- 20th century; Dramatists -- Texas
Document Types
Correspondence
Subjects (Persons)
King, Larry L.
- Books, 1959-1976
  Series Description
  This series contains drafts, galley proofs and jackets for books by Larry L. King. Titles include One-Eyed Man (1966), …And Other Dirty Stories (1968), Of Outlaws, Con Men, Whores, Politicians, and Other Artists (1980), The Whorehouse Papers (1981), None But the Blockhead (1986), and Because of Lozo Brown (1988). Also included are drafts from an early unpublished novel, "The Back of a Bear," research material for a never-realized book on Lyndon Baines Johnson, and a file of articles gathered together for Warning: Writer at Work, published by TCU Press. The material is arranged in chronological order.
  - "The Back of a Bear," (unpublished manuscript) (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - One-Eyed Man, drafts and book jacket (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - ...And Other Dirty Stories, book jacket (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - LBJ research (Box 1, Folder 7-11, Box 2, Folder 1-4)
  - Of Outlaws, Con Men, Whores, Politicians and Other Artists, book jacket (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - None But a Blockhead, galley proofs (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
  - None But a Blockhead, galley proofs and book jacket (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - The Whorehouse Papers, galley proofs (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Collection file and articles for TCU Press (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
  - Because of Lozo Brown, galley proof and book jacket (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Plays, 1977-1993
  This series, arranged in chronological order, contains material related to the writing, production and reception of the following theatrical works: The Best Little Whorehouse in Texas, The Kingfish, The Night Hank Williams Died, That Terrible Night Santa Got Lost In The Woods, The Golden Shadows Old West Museum, and The Best Little Whorehouse Goes Public. Many of the manuscripts include letters from King explaining the history and background of the drafts.
  The Best Little Whorehouse in Texas, co-written with Peter Masterson is based on King's 1974 Playboy article. It was first produced in showcase production at Actor's Studio, New York City, October 27-November 12, 1977. It then opened off-Broadway at Intermedia Theatre in April 1978, and moved to Broadway's 46th Street Theatre, on June 19, 1978, where its success supported 1,584 performances over the next four and half years and garnered King a Tony award nomination.
  The files in this series include scripts, sheet music, screenplay drafts, a playbook, playbills, posters, flyers, reviews, clippings, photographs, tickets, T-shirts, a jacket, promotional buttons, congratulations and a 1981 cartoon by Patrick Oliphant drawn on a napkin.
  The Kingfish, a one-man play about the flamboyant Louisiana Governor Huey P. Long, was written with long-time friend and Texas legislator, Ben Z. Grant. Found here are scripts, programs, playbills, the SMU Press book jacket and clippings.
  The Night Hank Williams Died premiered at the Memphis State University theatre. After several revisions, the play received its world premiere in Washington, D.C. in 1988. The following year it opened Off-Broadway. For this play, King received the Theatre Lobby Trust's 1988 Mary Goldwater Award for his contribution as playwright and actor and the 1989 Helen Hayes Award for best new play. These files contain scripts, correspondence on rewrites and production prospects, congratulations, awards, flyers, posters, playbills, audition notes, reviews, clippings, SMU Press proofs, a playbook and screenplays.
  The Golden Shadows Old West Museum was also tried out first in a workshop production at Memphis State University. These files contain a script, correspondence on revisions, playbills, flyers, reviews, and posters.
  In addition to the above material, this series includes an outline of The Best Little Whorehouse Goes Public, a playbook for a one-act play titled Christmas: 1933 and a playbill for the same one-act under the original title, That Terrible Night Santa Got Lost In The Woods, and a prospectus and treatment for "Road Story" an aborted project with Glenn Frey and Jimmy Buffett, put together by the New York producer Rocco Landesman.
  Also included in this series is research material and a script for a never-completed project on Lydia Thompson, an English burlesque queen who was all the rage in late 19th century America.
  - The Best Little Whorehouse in Texas, 1977-1991
    - Scripts, 1977-1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Sheet music: Words and music by Carol Hall (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Playbook, Samuel French, Inc. Inscribed by King (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Screenplay, first draft (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Screenplay, second draft (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Screenplay, final draft (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Playbills (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
    - Memorabilia (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - The Kingfish, 1977-1991
    - Original final transcript, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Script, as performed at John Houseman Theatre, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1977-1991 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Playbills (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Book jacket (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - The Life and Times of Miss Lydia Thompson" (unpublished), 1982-1992
    - Research on Zeffie and Lydia Thompson (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
    - Songs of the period (photocopies) (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
    - Script with cover letter and explanation by King, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - The Night Hank Williams Died, 1985-1990
    - Script, with letter from King, 1985, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Script, "Big Cast" version, with letter from King, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Original manuscript, with letter from King, May 1985 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Revised draft, signed by King, November 1985 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Revised draft, signed by King, December 1985 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Final "New York" version, signed by King, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Revised draft, "Final script for Rehearsals," signed by King, May 1986 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Revised draft, signed by King, May 1986 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - King's script used during production at New Playwright's Theatre, Washington, D.C., February 2 -March 6, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1986-1988 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Posters, flyers, awards (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Letters of congratulations, 1987-1988 (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
    - New York auditions (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Flyers, posters, reviews (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Playbills (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Clippings (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - SMU Press (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Final page proofs, SMU Press (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Script, "Acting edition," First printing, inscribed to Bill Wittliff (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Screenplay, First draft (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Screenplay, "1st Act," second draft, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Screenplay, second draft, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Screenplay, August 1990 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Christmas 1933 (playbook) and The Terrible Night Santa Got Caught in the Woods (playbill) (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - The Golden Shadows Old West Museum, 1985-1989
    - Script, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1985-1987 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Audition notes, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Ticket, playbill, reviews, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - "Road Story" prospectus & treatment, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - The Best Little Whorehouse Goes Public outline, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Articles, 1953-1991
  This series covers King's contributions to magazines and newspapers from his days with the Odessa-American in the 1950s, through his stint in Washington as editor of Capitol Hill, to his work for national magazines including Harper's, Life, Esquire, The Progressive, Sports Illustrated, Sport, Cosmopolitan, Playboy and Parade. The series contains tear sheets, and in some cases, whole copies of the magazine in which the article appeared. In addition, King's collection of The Texas Observer, to which he was a frequent contributor, is included. These issues have been removed from the plastic, colored, 3-ring binders in which King kept them. There are tear sheets for King's column for New Times and Washington Star, and newspaper clippings of his book reviews. The files contain galley proofs, magazines, cover pages, tear sheets and newspaper clippings and are arranged chronologically.
  - Odessa-American: J. Summy file, articles, and notes, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - The Texas Observer, 1960-1971
    - 1960-1961 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - December 1962 - July 1973 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - August - December 1963 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - January - June 1964 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - July - December 1964 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - January - June 1965 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - July - December 1965 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - January - June 1966 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - July - December 1966 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - January - June 1967 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - July - December 1967 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - January - June 1968 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - July - December 1968 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - January - June 1969 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - July - December 1969 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - January - June 1970 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - July - December 1970 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - January - June 1971 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - July - December 1971 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Capitol Hill (five issues), 1965 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - "Requiem for a West Texas Town," Harper's, January 1966 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - "Bob Jones University," Harper's, June 1966 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - "My Hero LBJ," Harper's, October 1966 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - "Joe Pool of HUAC," Harper's, November 1966 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - "God, Man and William F. Buckley," Harper's, March 1967 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - "Dear Congressman,.." New York Times Magazine, April 1967 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - "Roughing It In the Football Bushes," Harper's, August 1967 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - "The Cool World of Nelson Rockefeller," Harper's, February 1968 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - "An Epitaph for LBJ," Harper's, April 1968 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - "Hughes of Iowa," Harper's, March 1968 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - "Kids, Stray Dogs…" Harvard Crimson, February 11, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - "The Old Man," Harper's, April 1971 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - "Semi-Tough by Dan Jenkins" review Publisher's Weekly, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - "Spring Revels of the ABA," BookWorld, W. Post, June 4, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - "Most Likely to Succeed," New Times, November 16, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - "Wheeling and Dealing," Playboy, June 1978 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - "Don't let Amarillo Slim Psych You Out," Sport, November 1978 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - "He walked Across..." Congressional Record, October 29, 1979 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - "Hurtin' Good" Washington Post Magazine, February 13, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - "When Love Is Its Own Reward," Parade, May 8, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - "How the Army Brought Blacks" Parade, February 19, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - "A Tale of Two Teams," Parade, September 9, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - "This Is My Home," Parade, June 30, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - "Political Conventions," TV Guide, July 16, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - "Roots Christmas," TV Guide (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Love/Cheating proof, Texas Monthly, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - "What, Me Sixty?!!!," Parade, November 5, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - "Writers Si, Editors No!" Roundup Quarterly, Fall 1990 (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - "Vanishing Texas," final proofs, Texas Monthly, 1990 (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - Magazine Cover Pages (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - Tear Sheets, 1964-1966 (Box 11, Folder 29)
  - Tear Sheets, 1967-1978 (Box 12, Folder 1-4)
  - "Fulminations," New Times tear sheets, 1974-1976 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Washington Star, clippings, 1976-1977 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Tear Sheets, 1980-1991 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Book Reviews, 1965-1968 (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Short Stories, 1990
  This series contains only one file. Something Went With Daddy appeared in the literary journal, Story, in Autumn 1990. It contains the original manuscript, a final edit, and a copy of the journal.
  - Something Went With Daddy (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Television, 1981-1989
  King won an Emmy in 1982 for his television contribution, CBS Reports: The Best Little Statehouse in Texas, which first aired in August 1981. These files include a videotape and transcript of the show as well as a publicizing post card. Here also is a proposal for a TV series with a political setting.
  - CBS Reports: The Best Little Statehouse in Texas, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
  - Capitol Hill Proposal, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Song Lyrics, 1989-1990
  King penned some lyrics for his play The Night Hank Williams Died and later sold these along with others styled in a country and western vein in a package of ten. This series contains a demo tape and scratch notes for the songs. See also the Gary Cartwright Papers, Box 7, file 13 for a lyric King composed one night in New York with friend and fellow writer, Cartwright.
  - Songs (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Speeches, 1981-1993
  This series contains the invitations, announcements and flyers for functions King attended or participated in. Manuscripts of his speeches and the tape from the PEN Faulkner honors ceremony of 1990 are located here.
  - Speeches, 1988-1991 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    Contents
    Speech to the editors of National Geographic Magazine, Washington D.C., March 12, 1988
    Salute to Sarah McLendon, National Press Club, Washington D.C., November 26, 1990
    Lyndon Baines Johnson Distinguished Lectures, Southwest Texas State University, October 3, 1991
    Speech to Alcohol and Drug Counselors, Fairfax, VA, November 2, 1991
  - Pen Faulkner Honors, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Speech to Houston Alcohol and Drug Abuse Council (transcript and audio cassette), May 7, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Speech at Dobie-Webb-Bedichek fund raiser, Austin, TX, March 30, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Material About Larry L. King, 1957-1991
  This series contains clippings, interviews, a video, cartoons and research papers on King's writing career.
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1957-1991
    - 1957, 1968-1969, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - 1980-1984 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - 1986-1989 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Interview on Larry King Show (audio cassettes), May 24, 1982, March 6, 1986 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Radio interviews, one in Austin and two in Washington D.C. (audio cassettes), 1986, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Probe video (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Cartoons (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Research Papers about Larry L. King, 1973-1986, undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
    "The Best Little Writer in Texas," Leslie White Clay, Southern Methodist University, 1986
    "Perspectives on the South: The Writing of Willie Morris and Larry L. King," James B. Smith, Jr., University of Texas, May 21, 1973.
    "Ruminating and Relating in the Texas Essay," Clifford, Craig Edward, Tarleton State University, undated
- Other Writers, 1989-1993
  This series contains material, mostly clippings, King collected on contemporary writers. It includes a reminiscence of Billie Lee Brammer by Glenn Wilson of their days on Capitol Hill and a manuscript by Jack Runnel probably sent to King for his comments.
  - Billie Lee Brammer (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - James Lee Burke (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Aaron Latham, Edwin (Bud) Shrake (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - The Republic of Snakes by Jack Runnel, manuscript (Box 15, Folder 7-8)
- Personal Papers, 1929-1993
  This series contains personal records such as report cards, army discharge, birth and marriage certificates. There are photographs of King, his family and friends, cancelled checks and tax records from the mid-1970s.
  - Vital Records (birth certificate, report card, army discharge papers, etc.) (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, 1897-1999
    - 1897, 1929-1950 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - 1950-1959 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - 1960-1969 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - 1970-1979 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - 1980-1989 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - 1990-1999 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Tax records, 1972-1978 (Box 17)
  - Tax receipts (Box 18, Folder 1-3)
- Correspondence, 1957-1993